Guide to the Richard Gurtiza Collection On Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Richard Gurtiza collection on Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance
1987-2001
1992-2000
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6161
6161-001
Gurtiza, Richard
.87 cubic ft. 2 boxes
Materials related to the national APALA organization and the Seattle APALA chapter
Richard Gurtiza is a Filipino American labor union activist and union officer originally from Wapato, Washington. Gurtiza is president of Region 37, Inlandboatman's Union of the Pacific, the marine division of the International Longshre and Warehouse Union. The union represents Alaska cannery workers, who from the 1930s onwards were largely Filipino Americans and Asian Americans. Gurtiza became a member of Local 37 in 1977 and became Regional Director of the IBU 1993.
Gurtiza was born in the small farming community of Wapato, Washington in the 1950s. Gurtiza was a founder of the local chapter of the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA), an American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations constituency organization for Asian American and Pacific Islander labor union members. Gurtiza was also on the national Executive Board of APALA
In the late 1970s, Gurtiza was part of a rank and file reform movement of activist Local 37 cannery workers to reform the union and fight for better working conditions. Gurtiza worked with Silme Domingo and Gene Viernes—the leaders of the Alaska Cannery Workers Association—to build the reform movement. After Domingo and Viernes were murdered in 1981, Gurtiza and other reformers won leadership positions and transformed Local 37.
Gurtiza remains active in the IBU/ILWU, the King County Labor Council, and the Washington State Labor Council.
Collection of mailings, newsletters, convention and conference materials collected by Seattle Filipino American labor activist and union officer Richard Gurtiza. Gurtiza was a founder of the local chapter of the Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance (APALA), an American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations constituency organization for Asian American and Pacific Islander labor union members. Gurtiza was also on the national Executive Board of APALA, and some of the materials consist of convention materials from the national organizations' founding in 1992, leadership and education conferences; correspondence and newsletters.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington
Records stored off site; advance notice required for use.
No restrictions on access.
2017-01-04
Gurtiza, Richard$vArchives; Asian Pacific American Labor Alliance; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Labor$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Labor movement$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Labor unions$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Records (Documents)
Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Labor History
- NEWSLETTERS, 1992-1999; Series I
  - APALA News, 1992, 1993, 1999 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Asianweek: Siding with Organized Labor, 1996 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Fliers and pamphlets, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 1/3)
- MAILINGS AND FORMS, undated; Series II
  - APALA New York Chapter jacket form, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Membership renewal, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - AFL-CIO applications, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
- SEATTLE APALA CHAPTER, 1993-1999; SERIES III
  - Seattle Chapter meetings, 1993 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Seattle Chapter By-Laws, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Binder 1: APALA Seattle 1 of 2, 1997 (Box-folder 1/9-1/10)
    Chapter information, political action, correspondence
  - Binder 1: APALA Seattle 2 of 2, 1997 (Box-folder 1/10)
    Miscellaneous and membership
  - Retreat Agenda and evaluations, 1999 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Memorandums, 1992-1993; Series 4
  - Executive Board members, 1992 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Draft Model By-Laws, July 13, 1992 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Memo and ballot, 1992 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - January APALA/ Organizing Institute Training Program, 1993 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Materials available, Start-up funding, 1992 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Memorandums, February, 1993 (Box-folder 1/17)
- PROPOSALS AND POLICIES, 1987-1993; SERIES V
  - Policy on Clearance of Targets: Texas Triangle Organizing Committee, 1987 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Proposal Draft: The "Seattle Plan" Organizing Immigrant and Ethnic Communities, 1993 (Box-folder 1/19)
- CONVENTION MATERIALS, 1992-2001; SERIES VI
  - National Convention invitations, 1992, 1993, 1995 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Founding Convention resolution, 1992 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Founding Convention brochures, 1992 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - National Convention Materials: Los Angeles, August, 1993 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - National Convention Materials: New York City, August, 1995 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - National Convention Materials: San Francisco, August, 1997 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - National Convention Materials: Washington, D.C., August, 1999 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - National Convention Materials: Honolulu, Hawaii, August, 2001 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Binder 2: APALA Founding Convention: Making an Impact 1 of 2, 1992 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Convention agenda, convention floorplan, rules and procedures, APALA constitution
  - Binder 2: APALA Founding Convention: Making an Impact 2 of 2, 1992 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Convention resolutions, APALA chapter, AFL-CIO, Convention pre-registration list
- LEADERSHIP AND EDUCATION CONFERENCE, 1994; SERIES VII
  - Invitations and program, 1994 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Conference materials, 1994 (Box-folder 2/4)
- ELECTIONS, 2000; SERIES IIX
  - Election 2000 and Beyond, August, 2000 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - APALA Vote 2000 (Box-folder 2/6)
- EXECUTIVE BOARD MEETINGS, 1998-2001; SERIES IX
  - Executive Board Meeting, Los Angeles, California, 1998 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Executive Board Meeting, Las Vegas, Nevada, March, 1999 (Box-folder 2/8-2/9)
  - Executive Board Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1999 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Executive Board Meeting, Honolulu, Hawaii, 2001 (Box-folder 2/11)
- MISCELLANEOUS, 1993; SERIES X
  - Settings, manual, undated (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Letter, 1993 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - APALA note pages, undated (Box-folder 2/14)